Guide to the Enoch A. Bryan Papers 1843-1989
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 4. Materials acquired with personal papers in Bryan Family, circa 1990
  - Series 4.1. Speeches and essays
    - Literature
      - On Plato's Philosophy (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - Shakespeare's Queen Catherine (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - Aristotle on Plato's Communism (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - Sartor Resartus (book review) (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - The Chameleon and Metamorphic Rocks (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - Portia, an Italian Girl (Shakespeare study) (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - William Shakespeare (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - The Holy Grail in Literature (Box 13, Folder 117)
      - The School for Husbands (play) (Box 13, Folder 117)
    - The Unification of Italy, several drafts (Box 13, Folder 118)
    - Addresses and Essays
      - Americanization (Box 13, Folder 119)
      - Untitled, on Immigration (Box 13, Folder 119)
      - Untitled, on Jean Bodin (Box 13, Folder 119)
      - My Confession of Faith (Box 13, Folder 119)
    - Land Tenure History
      - Recent Discussions on the Mark Theory (Box 13, Folder 120)
      - The Theory of Village Community as presented by Sir H. Maine (Box 13, Folder 121)
      - The Origins of Property in Land (Box 13, Folder 122)
      - Other Land Tenure Notes (Box 13, Folder 122)
      - Notes, etc, re: United States Public Lands (Box 13, Folder 123)
    - Petition to Congress for purchase of Western Lands (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Essays
      - Montague B[illeg] Cinque Ports; Economics 3, Harvard Univ, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 125)
      - American History (magazine), Aug 1892, with article re: the founding of Post Vincennes (Box 13, Folder 125)
      - Historical Notes (Box 13, Folder 125)
      - Fragment (page 2 forward) re: American commerce in Asia (Box 13, Folder 125)
      - Memorandum of an Analysis of what a History of the Northern Pacific should contain (Box 13, Folder 125)
      - Memorandum on the Agricultural Development of the Northwest (Box 13, Folder 125)
      - Untitled, on history of London (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - Untitled, on history of Rome and Italy (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - Germany and the Germans; Woman's Place in Society and her Proper Preparation for it (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - The Bright Side of the Teacher's Life (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - On the Death of President Garfield (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - Fragment (p. 2 forward) on history of education (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - For the Bible Society (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - The Spirit of the Land-Grant Institutions (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - Untitled, re: tribute to Mrs. (Solon) Shedd (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - A National System of Education (Box 13, Folder 126)
      - The Truth Shall set You Free (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - The Democratic vs Aristicratic View of Education (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Untitled, re: personal recollection of WSC in 1890s (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - The Present Status of Scientific Education and How it Came to Pass (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Founding the State College (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Untitled, re: draft of talk to an education association (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - The State School of Mines (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - The Master Teacher (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Extract from Address to Spokane High School, 1905 (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Address at Commencement, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 127)
      - Tribute to James Albert Woodburn (Box 14, Folder 127)
    - Essays and speeches
      - Recent Economic Progress of American Women (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Untitled, to Seattle High School, 1901; Diversified Farming (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Untitled, to teachers of Spokane County (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Unitled, notes on history of college curriculum in 1820 (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Nansen and Nordenshiold; Recollections (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Is Economic a Universal Science? (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Emulation Fragment and notes re: land history, constitutional history, etc. Cambridge, 1892 (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - The Relation of Higher Education to the Community (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Christian education -- fragment (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Fragment (p.4 ff.) on education (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Untitled, opens, "A child's education (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Three Subjects for Talks (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - The Art and Science of Education (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Fragments (literary and poetic) (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Adherence to Truth in Art (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Resume of the Education Situation in Idaho (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - A True Ghost Story; The Farmer and Labor; Federal Aids (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - The Economic Development of the Pacific Northwest (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Industrial Democracy (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - Cooperative Work between Stations and the Department of Agriculture (Box 14, Folder 128)
      - On the Occassion of the Inaugaration of President E. O. Holland (Box 14, Folder 128)
    - Fragments of essays and speeches (Box 14, Folder 129)
    - Two MSS, possibly authored by Hattie Bryan, but in handwriting of EAB (Box 14, Folder 130)
    - Manuscripts by persons other than E. A. Bryan
      - Toast to E. A. Bryan, June 1910 (Box 14, Folder 131)
      - Julius Galland Trust Fund (Box 14, Folder 131)
      - F. A. Golder (Facetious autobiography) (Box 14, Folder 131)
  - Series 4.2. Personal records and papers
    - Legal and Financial Documents, E.A. Bryan, Family members, Pullman Presbyterian Church, 1866-1902 (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Legal and Financial Documents, 1877-1922 (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - Account, E.A. Bryan, 1877-1890 (Box 15, Folder 133.1)
    - Estate of E. Bryan, 1941 (Box 15, Folder 134)
    - Account Books of E. A Bryan, 1877-1896 (Box 15, Folder 135)
    - Family documents and notes, 1843-1989 (Box 15, Folder 136)
    - Indiana University, 1877, and "History of the Class of 78" (Box 15, Folder 137)
    - Grayville, Illinois, materials, chiefly newspaper column by E. A. Bryan, 1867-1882 (Box 15, Folder 138)
    - Vincennes University materials, 1887-1892 (Box 15, Folder 139)
    - Trips to Europe, 1906-1912 (Box 15, Folder 140)
    - Calling cards, announcements, meeting badges, etc., 1879-1927 (Box 16, Folder 141)
    - Newsclips and newspapers, circa 1892-96 (Box 16, Folder 142)
    - Newsclips and newspapers, re: churches, 1887-1933 (Box 16, Folder 143)
    - Honorific Material, certificates of appreciation, University Diplomas, etc., 1878-1941 (Box 16, Folder 144)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets: Ernest Lindsay, "The State College of Washington: A Land-Grant College" (1940), Indiana University annual report (1884-1885), Indiana School Journal issue (volume 37, number 2), Memorial of the Indiana State Teachers Association to the General Assembly (1887)., 1885-1940 (Box 17, Folder 148)
  - Series 4.3. Riviera Company
    - Correspondence, legal and financial documents, 1910-1937 (Box 17, Folder 145)
    - Checks, sight drafts, etc., 1910-1914 (Box 17, Folder 146)
    - "Enoch Bryan Utopia", by Jay Kalez (A map of Riviera was seperated and placed with WSU Libraries Historic Map Collection) (Box 17, Folder 147)